Register of the N. A. (Nestor Apollonovich) Lakoba Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
N. A. (Nestor Apollonovich) Lakoba Papers
1915-1939
2003C73
Lakoba, N. A. (Nestor Apollonovich), 1893-1936.
3 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (1.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Nestor Apollonovich Lakoba (1893-1936) papers document life and activities of the politician, revolutionary, party and government official, and victim of the purges.
Administrative Information
Access
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2003
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1893 May 1 Born, Village of Lykhny, Abkhaziia
1910-1911 Studied at the seminary in Tiflis, Georgia
1912 Became a member of the Russian Social Democratic party
1912-1918 Worked for the Russian Social Democratic party in Abkhaziia and Groznyi
1918 Led the uprising against the Menshevik-dominated government of Abkhaziia Deputy chairman of the Sukhumi Military Revolutionary Committee (Georgia); organized detachments of partisan forces for combat during the Russian Civil War
Late 1918 Arrested and imprisoned in Sukhumi, Georgia
1919 Banished from Georgia
1920 Took control of the underground Bolshevik organization in the city of Batumi (Georgia)
1921 Assistant chairman of the Revolutionary Committee in Abkhaziia
1922 Chairman of the Council of People's Commissars of the Abkhaziian ASSR
1930-1936 Chairman of the Central Executive Committee of Abkhaziia; served on the Central Executive Committee of the Georgian SSR, the Central Executive Committee of the Transcaucasian SFSR, the Central Executive Committee of the USSR and the Bureau of the Party Central Committee in Georgia. He was personally acquainted with his fellow Caucasians Joseph Stalin and Lavrentii Beriia
1936 December 28 Died unexpectedly. Lakoba had an honorable burial, but was later declared an "enemy of the people"
Scope and Content of Collection
Nestor Apollonovich Lakoba (1893-1936) papers document life and activities of the politician, revolutionary, party and government official, and victim of the purges.
A Caucasian revolutionary before 1917, Nestor Lakoba was appointed chairman of the Council of People's Commissars of the Abkhaziian Autonomous Soviet Socialist Republic, and from 1930 to 1936 was chairman of the Central Executive Committee of that republic. He served on the Central Executive Committee of the Georgian Soviet Socialist Republic, the Central Executive Committee of the Transcaucasian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic, the Central Executive Committee of the USSR and the Bureau of the Party Central Committee in Georgia. Since 1917 he was personally acquainted with his fellow Caucasians Joseph Stalin and Lavrentii Beriia. Both later considered him their personal enemy. Majority of people believe he was poisoned by Beriia's agents. He was given a state funeral, but posthumously declared an enemy of the people.
The bulk of the collection is hand written letters between Nestor Lakoba and the leaders of the Russian revolution and high ranking Soviet government officials such as Joseph Stalin, Feliks Dzerzhinskii, Lavrentii Beriia, Sergo Ordzhonikidze, and many others. Correspondence includes letters of both a business and personal nature arranged chronologically.
Photographic series contains a huge bulk of very unique and unknown prints of Soviet leaders, such as Joseph Stalin, Feliks Dzerzhinskii, Lavrentii Beriia, Sergo Orgdzhonikidze, Mikhail Kalinin, Semen Budennyi, as well as Stalin's children Svetlana and Vasilii.
Documentation in the Speeches and Writings includes drafts, notes, sayings, verses, theses, speeches, and final published articles as well as other materials relating to his public life.
Of particular interest is the Biographical file with different versions of autobiographies and curriculum vitae, as well as other materials reflecting his early years in Georgia in general and in Abkhaziia in particular.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series: Biographical file, Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Subject file, and Photographs
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Soviet Union--Politics and government--1917-1936.; Georgia (Republic)--Politics and government--1917-1991.; Abkhaziia (Georgia)--Politics and government.; Stalin, Joseph, 1879-1953.
Collection Contents
- Biographical file, 1915-1939.
  Includes autobiography, curriculum vitae, certificates of graduation, jail documents, medical records, and notebook pages with addresses, phone numbers, notes, and sayings arranged by form
  - Notebook pages. (Folder 1: 1)
    Includes addresses, phone numbers, notes, sayings, undated
  - Autobiography, 1936 February 12 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Curriculum vitae, 1936 October 14 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Certificate of graduation, Tiflis seminary, 1915 May 6 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Certificate, honorary leader of children communist movement of Abkhaziia, Georgia, 1924 August 22 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Lakoba case, Sukhumi jail, 1918 November-December (Folder 1: 6)
  - Medical records, X-Ray results, 1926, 1935 (Folder 1: 7)
- Correspondence, 1922-1939.
  Contains correspondence of both business and personal nature. Arranged chronologically by date
  - General
    - Undated, unidentified
      - General (Folder 1: 8)
      - Letter from Kostia regarding pursuit of bandits Chkhopeliia and Sichinava (Folder 1: 9)
      - Unfinished letter in purple ink regarding upcoming visit of L. Beriia to Sukhumi (Folder 1: 10)
      - Note from Dzhemal (Folder 1: 11)
    - 1925-1932, unidentified (Folder 1: 12)
    - Cables, mostly undated. Includes cables from 1927 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Adamii and Chitai, official letter, Undated (Folder 1: 14)
  - Kuchuloriia, D. I., People's Commissar of Provision, Georgian Soviet Socialist Republic, Undated (Folder 1: 15)
  - Pirunov, comrade, Undated (Folder 1: 16)
  - Meskhishvili, 1922 June 15 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Ordzhonikidze, Sergo (chairman of the Central Control Commission), 1922-1928 (Folder 1:)
    - letter to N. Lakoba with a request to send 16.5 million Deutschmarks to Mr. Schreiber, who lives in Berlin. Probably these are party money earmarked for the support of the German Communist Party, Undated (Folder 1: 18)
    - note to N. Lakoba asking to accommodate his old friend Sergei Anishchev arriving in Sukhumi on vacation, Undated (Folder 1: 19)
    - letter to Atarbekov regarding the visit of Feliks Dzerzhinskii, Genrikh IAgoda, and others to Sukhumi in mid-October, 1922 April 17 (Folder 1: 20)
    - letter regarding a visit of Feliks Dzerzhinskii, Genrikh IAgoda, and other people to Sukhumi, 1922 May 15 (Folder 1: 21)
    - letter to N. Lakoba regarding Sergo Ordzhonikidze, 1923 August 22 (Folder 1: 22)
    - letter to N. Lakoba regarding medical leave of Leon Trotsky to Sukhumi, 1924 January 18 (Folder 1: 23)
    - note to N. Lakoba regarding Abkhazian situation, 1925 September 27 (Folder 1: 24)
    - draft letter from N. Lakoba to Sergo Ordzhonikize, 1926 January 7 (Folder 1: 25)
    - letter regarding Molotov's trip to Sukhumi, 1926 November 29 (Folder 1: 26)
    - letter to N. Lakoba asking to arrange a stay in Sukhumi for a military attach Vitalii Primakov, 1928 October 18 (Folder 1: 27)
    - Belen'kii, A., letter to N. Lakoba regarding doctor's advice to Leon Trotsky to immediately take a trip to the south, 1924 January 6 (Folder 1: 28)
    - Dzerzhinskii, Feliks (organized the first Soviet institutions of police coercion and terror), 1924 January 18 (Folder 1: 29)
    - official confidential letter from Sofronov, signed as head of the Black Sea fleet, 1924 February 13 (Folder 1: 30)
    - official letter from the State Black Sea-Azov steam-ship line, 1924 March 21 (Folder 1: 31)
    - Prosecutor General of Abkhaziia (Georgia), office memo regarding death sentence to Zholkver, A., 1924 September 25 (Folder 1: 32)
  - Beriia, Lavrentii, head of the People's Commissariat for Internal Affairs (NKVD), 1924-1932 (Folder 1:)
    - copy of the letter from N. Lakoba regarding Stalin's request to find a candidate to fill the position of Secretary of the Transcaucasian Regional Communist Committee, Undated (Folder 1: 33)
    - defending a famous secret service officer, Undated (Folder 1: 34)
    - confirming appointment of comrade Dzhavakhov to a senior position in the Sukhumi CheKa (secret police), 1924 November 12 (Folder 1: 35)
    - letter to N. Lakoba asking him to familiarize himself with the case of Comrades Sadzhaia and TSaralov. Includes L. Beriia's signature on the letterhead of the Tanscaucasian CheKa (secret police), 1924 November 19 (Folder 1: 36)
    - secret service travel identification card for protection of comrade Leon Trotsky, 1925 January 27 (Folder 1: 37)
    - letter to N. Lakoba concerning two sick workers, 1928 September 14 (Folder 1: 38)
    - 1929 October 29 (Folder 1: 39)
    - copy of the letter which describes a conversation between N. Lakoba and Stalin regarding Secretary of the Transcaucasian Regional Communist Party Committee Mamiia Orakhelashvili, 1932 June 21 (Folder 1: 40)
    - letter "the copy of our report note", 1932 July 26 (Folder 1: 41)
    - Draft letter to L. Beriia (with copies to Stalin, Kaganovich, Molotov, and Rudzutak) regarding pronouncement received by N. Lakoba on December 21, 1932, 1932 December (Folder 1: 42)
    - Georg (possibly Georgii Sturua), 1925 January 26 (Folder 1: 43)
    - TSanava, Sergei, 1925 August 7 (Folder 1: 44)
    - Orakhelashvili. M., secretary of the Transcaucasian Regional Communist Party Committee, 1926 January 4 (Folder 1: 45)
    - Lakoba, Mikhail (N. Lakoba's step brother), 1926 (Folder 1:)
    - strictly confidential, Undated (Folder 1: 46)
    - He was assigned to Leon Trotsky as head of the secret police guard during Trotsky's stay in Abkhaziia, 1926 May 23. (Folder 1: 47)
    - V. Pantsulai, famous Georgian Menshevik. He is expressing concern about Russian policy in Georgia in general and in Abkhaziia in particular, 1926 June 10 (Folder 1: 48)
    - Tuskiia, S., 1927 June 16 (Folder 1: 49)
    - Inal-Ip, N., 1927 October 4 (Folder 1: 50)
    - Gugushvili. V., 1927 November 1 (Folder 1: 51)
    - Birvava, P., 1927 November 8 (Folder 1: 52)
    - Bzhalava, Manuchar, 1929, April 19 (Folder 1: 53)
  - Stalin, Joseph, 1929-1934 (Folder 1:)
    - Letter to Stalin in which N. Lakoba talks about his (N. Lakoba's) upcoming trip to America "for purchasing of planting material of citrus trees". Includes draft and final version, Undated (Folder 1: 54)
    - expressing disagreement with the decision of the Georgian Bolshevik Party's Central Committee (TSetlin's commission) regarding the Abkhaziian case, which recommended removing N. Lakoba from the position of president of the Central Executive Committee of Abhaziia, 1929 October 19 (Folder 1: 55)
    - response to Stalin's letter of October 19, 1929 late October (Folder 1: 56)
    - short evaluation of N. Lakoba's essay "Stalin i Khashim," which was published in October of the same year as an illustrative brochure by the Abhazian party press (20,000 copies), 1934 August 12 (Folder 1: 57)
  - CHichinadzhe letter, 1931 March 10 (Folder 1: 58)
  - Fedorov, Professor, letter regarding N. Lakoba's health, 1931 July 20 (Folder 1: 59)
  - Eliava, SHalva, Deputy People's Commissar of the Foreign Commerce of the USSR, 1931 August-November (Folder 1: 60)
  - SHaginian, Marietta, poet, 1932 October 16 (Folder 1: 61)
  - letter on stationery of the "Chairman of the All Union State Association Sovmongtuvtorg", 1932 May 18 (Folder 1: 62)
  - Karpov, L., 1932 November 23 (Folder 1: 63)
  - Leideker, S., 1933 February 9 (Folder 1: 64)
  - note from the Director of the Kholodnorechensk construction project (Stalin's "dacha" - summer vacation residence), 1933 February 20 (Folder 1: 65)
  - CHakvetadze, head of "Traktotsentr", 1933 November 15 (Folder 1: 66)
  - Kalandiia, Markoz, 1933 November 29 (Folder 1: 67)
  - Ivashchenko, Mikhail, 1934 January 11 (Folder 1: 68)
  - office memo on the stationery of the Chairman of the State Political Administration, 1934 February 26 (Folder 1: 69)
  - Agrba, Z., 1934 October 15 (Folder 1: 70)
  - Petiaev, S. People's Commissar of Agriculture of Abkhaziia, 1934 December 28 (Folder 1: 71)
  - Borisova, A., 1936 February (Folder 1: 72)
  - letter to N. Lakoba from General Vlasik, head of Stalin's secret police guards, 1936 May 31 (Folder 1: 73)
  - Musabekov, G., secretary of the Transcaucasian Regional Communist Party Committee, 1936 November (Folder 1: 74)
  - letter from Mardaleishvili, 1939 September 12 (Folder 1: 75)
- Speeches and writings, 1921-1937.
  Contains of Nestor Lakoba's writings, speeches, reports, coded messages, and orders. Arranged chronologically
  - N. Lakoba sayings, Undated (Folder 2: 1-2)
  - notes, Undated (Folder 2: 3-4)
  - theses for speeches, Undated (Folder 2: 5-7)
  - Speech drafts
    - Undated (Folder 2: 8-10)
    - 1930s (Folder 2: 11-13)
  - request draft for a battalion of GPU from Tiflis for peasant suppression, Undated (Folder 2: 14)
  - report to the "Council of propaganda and action of the people's of the East about the political situation in Sultan (old) Turkey", 1921 (Folder 2: 15)
  - coded messages compiled by N. Lakoba, 1922 (Folder 2: 16)
  - article, Iskry Oktiabr'skoi revoliutsii, Sukhumi. Printed copy, 1922 (Folder 2: 17)
  - speech at a meeting of senior workers, 1922 November 18 (Folder 2: 18)
  - general thoughts regarding an exhibit of the achievements of the Caucasus economy, 1925/1926 (Folder 2: 19)
  - explanation regarding accusations laid down in the office memo of Prosecutor General of the USSR Akulov to Comrade Stalin, 1934 January (Folder 2: 20)
  - Stalin i KHashim: 1901-1902 gogy, (nekotorye epizody iz Batumskogo podpol'ia), Sukhumi, 1934
    - Theses of the manuscript, undated (Folder 2: 21)
    - Holograph and typescript, undated (Folder 2: 22)
    - Printed copy, 1934 (Folder 2: 23)
  - Ot VI k VII S'iezdu Sovetov ASSR Abkhazii, Sukhumi. Printed copy, 1935 (Folder 2: 24)
  - speech praising the project of the new Soviet Constitution, 1936 (Folder 2: 25)
  - speech at the celebratory meeting of the Sukhumi city council devoted to the opening of the railroad Ochamchire-Kelasuri, 1936 January 1 (Folder 2: 26)
  - speech, "Progress report on the question of storage of tobacco supplies in Abkhaziia", 1936 January 4 (Folder 2: 27)
  - order, directions and requests ("strictly confidential") for building a two room cottage, 1936 October (Folder 2: 28)
  - Strictly confidential letter from investigator Pertsov, 1937 February 17 (Folder 2: 29)
- Subject file, 1914-1936.
  Arranged Alphabetically
  - evaluation of work methods of Comrade TSeitlin in the city of Gudauta., Undated (Folder 2: 30)
    Typescript. Includes handwritten notes
  - letter to Anton Ivanovich from unidentified correspondent, Undated (Folder 2: 31)
  - survey, "Agriculture of Abkhaziia - base of the Soviet food industry" (pp.8-24 are missing), Undated (Folder 2: 32)
  - questionnaire for "The history of the civil war in Abkhaziia", Undated (Folder 2: 33)
  - letter (21 pages) from the people of the Abkhaziian Autonomous Republic to Comrade Stalin, Undated (Folder 2: 34)
  - complaint regarding false accusations to the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Georgia, unidentified, Undated (Folder 2: 35)
  - reference material about geranium planting, Undated (Folder 2: 36)
  - bank document and check, 1914 October 14 (Folder 2: 37)
  - appreciation letter to Doctor Sil'chenko, 1921 (Folder 2: 38)
  - Miriantsev, Georgii, promissory note, 1923 (Folder 2: 39)
  - case of bandits CHkhopeliia and Sichinava. Includes list of crimes committed, 1924 (Folder 2: 40)
  - minutes of meetings, Caucasian Regional Control Commission, Russian Communist Bolshevik Party, 1924-1925 (Folder 2: 41)
  - Kadyrov, Seid, report ("strictly confidential") on the national question in Georgia, 1929 May (Folder 2: 42)
  - Kolokolkin, V., note, Early 1930s (Folder 3: 1)
  - Danchin, Valerian Dmitrievich, curriculum vitae, 1930 August 7 (Folder 3: 2)
  - council of the Tkvarchel'skii collective farm, progress report, 1931 January-August (Folder 3: 3)
  - Rubtsov, L. I., description of the local tree "prutniak" or "Avraamovo derevo" (Vitex Agnus Castus), 1934 December 31 (Folder 3: 4)
  - excerpts from the newspaper Pravda, 1935 April 5 and 19 (Folder 3: 5-6)
  - KHatuntsev, letter to his doctor, 1936, October 14 (Folder 3: 7)
- Photographs, undated.
  Mostly undated, including many 1930s images. Arranged by topic
  - N. Lakoba
    - Portrait (Folder 3: 8-9)
    - On a tribune (Folder 3: 10)
    - In a parade (Folder 3: 11)
    - In automobile (Folder 3: 12)
    - In the airplane named after him Looking through an open window (Folder 3: 13)
  - N. Lakoba with Soviet and party officials
    - Joseph Stalin, Mikhail Kalinin, and others (Folder 3: 14)
    - Sergo Ordzhinikidzhe, Semen Budennyi, and others (Folder 3: 15)
    - L. Beriia, A Khandzhian, and others (Folder 3: 16)
    - L. Beriia, and others on steps of an office building (Folder 3: 17)
    - N. Lakoba, L. Beriia, Sarie Lakoba (N. Lakoba's wife), and others (Folder 3: 18)
    - Group of delegates (including N. Lakoba) of the VIIth All-Union Congress of the Council of People Deputies (Folder 3: 19)
    - Guests at home (Folder 3: 20)
    - Guests in the Botanical garden (Folder 3: 21-22)
    - Friends on a wooden bridge (Folder 3: 23)
    - Lev Kamenev with hunting trophies (Folder 3: 24)
    - In his native village Lykhny with Moscow guests (Folder 3: 25-26)
    - Group of people in front of the Duke's home in Lykhny village (Folder 3: 27)
    - Abkhaziian party (Folder 3: 28)
    - Two other horsemen (Folder 3: 29)
    - Horsemen in mountains (Folder 3: 30)
    - Group of people sitting on a bench (Folder 3: 31)
    - Bolsheviks in an automobile (Folder 3: 32)
    - L. Beriia in N. Lakoba's car (Folder 3: 33)
    - L. Beriia, Nina Gegechkori (his wife), Svetlana Stalina and others (on a ship) (Folder 3: 34-35)
    - Series of photographs depicting L. Beriia flirting with a woman (Folder 3: 36)
    - L. Beriia, Khandzhian, and Musabekov (Folder 3: 37)
    - L. Beriia on a tribune (Folder 3: 38)
  - Friends and family
    - Vasilii Stalin, Nina Gegechkori (L. Beriia's wife), and Sarie Lakoba (N. Lakoba's wife) (Folder 3: 39)
    - Nina Gegechkori (L. Beriia's wife), Svetlana Stalina, Sarie Lakoba (N. Lakoba's wife), and Nazie Dzhikhashvili (N. Lakoba's relative) (Folder 3: 40)
    - IAkov Dzhugashvili (Stalin's son), Svetlana Stalina, and Rauf Lakoba (N. Lakoba's son) (Folder 3: 41)
    - Sergo Ordzhonikidzhe with Rauf (N. Lakoba's son), group picture (Folder 3: 42)
    - Svetlana Stalina and L. Beriia (Folder 3: 43)
  - Funeral
    - General (Folder 3: 44-46)
    - Memorial service (Folder 3: 47)
    - L. Beriia helping to carry N. Lakoba's coffin (Folder 3: 48)
    - Funeral wreath from L. Beriia and his wife Nina Gegechkori (Folder 3: 49)
  - 3 strips of contact prints (Folder 3: 50)
  - 1933 September, 1 photo album with inscription "To Comrade Lakoba". Depicts vacation images of Joseph Stalin, L. Beriia, N. Lakoba, and many others (Folder 4)